<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The antient, true, and admirable history of patient Grisel a poore mans daughter in France: shewing, how maides, by her example, in their good behauiour may marrie rich husbands: and likewise, wiues by their patience and obedience may gaine much glorie. Written first in French. And therefore to French I speake and giue direction. For English dames will liue in no subiection. But now translated into English. Therefore say not so. For English maids and wiues surpasse the French, in goodnesse of their liues.</title>
            <title>Decamerone. Day 10. Novel 10. English</title>
            <author>Boccaccio, Giovanni, 1313-1375.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118969</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854176</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854176</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19585</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19585)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 959:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The antient, true, and admirable history of patient Grisel a poore mans daughter in France: shewing, how maides, by her example, in their good behauiour may marrie rich husbands: and likewise, wiues by their patience and obedience may gaine much glorie. Written first in French. And therefore to French I speake and giue direction. For English dames will liue in no subiection. But now translated into English. Therefore say not so. For English maids and wiues surpasse the French, in goodnesse of their liues.</title>
                  <title>Decamerone. Day 10. Novel 10. English</title>
                  <author>Boccaccio, Giovanni, 1313-1375.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. L[ownes] for William Lugger; and are to be sold at his shop in Bedlem, neere Moore-Field,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Based on day 10, novel 10 of: Boccaccio, Giovanni. Decamerone.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The history of patient Grisel.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imprint shaved, affecting date.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Griselda (Legendary character) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Italian fiction --  Translations into English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19585:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19585:1"/>
            <p>THE ANTIENT, True, and Admirable Hiſtory <hi>Of Patient</hi> GRISEL, <hi>A Poore Mans Daughter in</hi> France: Shewing, <hi>How Maides, by her example, in their good</hi> behauiour may marrie rich <hi>HVSBANDS;</hi> AND Likewiſe, Wiues by their patience and obedience <hi>may gaine much Glorie.</hi> Written firſt in French. AND
<q>
                  <l>Therefore to French I ſpeake and giue direction.</l>
                  <l>For, Engliſh Dames will liue in no ſubiection.</l>
               </q> But, now Tranſlated into Engliſh. AND
<q>
                  <l>Therefore ſay not ſo. For, Engliſh maids and wiues</l>
                  <l>Surpaſſe the French, in goodneſſe of their liues.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>William Lugger;</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Bedlem, neere Moore-Fields. 1610.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:19585:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19585:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE Hiſtorie of patient GRISEL, made</hi> Marchioneſſe of <hi>Saluſs.</hi> In which is <hi>exemplified the true obedience, and</hi> noble behauiour of vertuous women towards their Husbands.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. How the Marqueſſe of <hi>Saluſs</hi> paſſed the time of his youth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any deſire of mariage, till he was requeſted by the faire entreatie of a fauorite, and other Gentlemen, to affect a wife; both for the good of the Country, and the honour of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: with his anſwer to the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Etweene the Mountaines of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the South, lyes the territory of <hi>Salus,</hi> a Country flouriſhing with excellent Townes and Caſtles, and peopled with the beſt ſort of Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and Peaſants: amongſt whom there liued not long ſince a Nobleman, of great hope and expectation, Lord of the Cnuntry, by name, <hi>Gualter,</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſs:</hi> to whom, as the gouernment a pertained by right of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; ſo their obedience attended, by deſert of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe. He was young in yéeres, noble of lineage, and ſuch attractiue demeanor, that the beſt thought it a pleaſure to bée commanded by him, and the worſt grew more tractable by his good example: his delight was in hunting and hawking, and the pleaſure of the time preſent extinguiſhed the care of the time to come; for he thought not of mariage, nor to intangle himſelfe with the inconueniences of a wife, till at laſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:19585:3"/> and Noblemen of his Country proiected the contrary, as diſcontented to ſée him indiſpoſed that way, and preſaging a kind of proſperity to themſelues, if by his mariage poſteritie might ariſe to aſſure them the better, how they might beſtow their obedience hereafter. Whereupon, they aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and made one day amongſt the reſt a determiner of their reſolutions, chooſing out for their ſpeaker a Noble Knight, of great authority, faire demeanor, eloquent ſpéech, and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with the Marqueſſe then any of the reſt: who, thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with all their mindes, and prepared to vtter his owne minde, tooke an opportunity to acquaint the renowned Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe with the matter.</p>
               <p>Moſt Honourable Sir, the great humanity extended to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs, &amp; of which I moſt eſpecially haue participated, hath thus emboldened me aboue others, to make a further triall of your patience, and forbearing my rudenes; not that there is any ſufficiency or ſingularity in me aboue others: but in that héeretofore I haue found you ſo generous toward all, I make no queſtion to finde you as gratious toward my ſelfe; and in that it hath pleaſed you to accept of our loue, wee are proud againe to be vnder your obedience: wherein we ſhall reioice the more, if you now accord to our requeſt the ſooner, which is, to marry without delay. The time paſſeth, and will not be recalled: your youth intreats it, and muſt not be demed: your countrey importunes it, and would not bee oppoſed: your neighbours deſire it, and hope to bee ſatisfied: and all ſorts requeſt it, and wiſh it for your honour. For when age approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, death attends it at the héeles, &amp; no man can tell when, or how it will fall vpon him. Therefore wee humbly requeſt you to accept our ſupplications, and accord to this importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that we may prouide by your appointment, a lady wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your honour and our ſubiection. In this wee are the more ſuppliant, becauſe it will rebound ſo much to the good of your countrey, and the enlarging your renowne: for if it ſhould ſo fall out (which God forbid) that you die without iſſue, we may lament the loſſe of our lord, but not redreſſe the complaints of the people: we ſhall want you that was al our
<pb facs="tcp:19585:3"/> comfort, but are ſure of diſtreſſe to our euerlaſting trouble. If then you either loue your ſelfe, or pity vs, frame a heart to this impreſſion, and leaue not vs to further feare and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet.</p>
               <p>When the noble lord had thus apprehended the petition of his louing ſubiects, he reſolued to anſwer them as gratiouſly as they had propounded the buſineſſe with regard of duty, and ſo replied: My deareſt friends, you haue vrged mee to a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in which as yet I haue beene a mere ſtranger: for by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I delight in liberty, and by cuſtome continued my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; both which muſt needs bee curbed by mariage, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by taking a wife: notwithſtanding, I caſt awaie all doubts, to pleaſure you; and will thinke of no incombrances ſo you be ſatisfied. For though mariage hath many difficulties attending; eſpecially, the feare of legitimation in our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſuſpicion of that honour which lies on our wiues ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, yet all ſhall bee ouercomne with this reſolution, that I ſhall pleaſe you in the ſame: for I am reſolued, if anie good come for mans contentment by marriage, it is from God; to whom I ſubmit this cauſe, and pray for the good ſucceſse of your wiſhes, that I may liue to maintaine your peace, as well as my owne pleaſure: and look wherein my contentment ſhall enlarge mine honour, your welfare ſhall be reſpected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue my life; ſo that (beleeue it) I will ſatisfie your demands, and apply my ſelfe to the purpoſe. Only one thing I requeſt at your hands, to take in worth my choice, and neither inſult if ſhe be a princeſſe of greatnes, nor repine if ſhe be of meane e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: but loue her becauſe I haue loued you, and regard her howſoeuer, in that ſhe is my wife; neither being curious nor inquiſitiue whom I will chuſe, nor diſaffected when it is paſt remedy.</p>
               <p>When the company had heard him out, and found him ſo willing to their ſatisfaction, they gaue him thankes with one heart for his kinde admiſſion, and anſwered with one tongue, he ſhould not finde them repugnant, but they would honor his wife as the princeſſe of the world, and be morigerous to him as the Commander of their ſoules. Thus did this new report
<pb facs="tcp:19585:4"/> (like a meſſenger of glad tidings) fill all the <hi>Marquiſate</hi> with ioy, and the palace with delight, when they vnderſtood their lord would marry, and in a manner heard the time appointed: for preſently it was proclaimed through the Countrey, and a day aſſigned for all commers to come to the Court. The No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles prepared themſelues in the beſt manner: the Ladies ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no coſt, either for ornaments of their bodies, or ſetting out their beauties: the Gentles flocked to pleaſe their lord, and were braue to ſet out their owne greatnes: the Citizens were rich in their neatnes, and handſome in their attire: the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers were formall in their ſhowes, and ſumptuous in their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants: the Countryman had his variety, and the verie Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant his brauery; in a word, al ſorts gloried in the hope of that feſtiuall, and euery mans expectation attended the day of the triumph. For neuer was ſuch a preparation in <hi>Saluſs</hi> before, nor ſuch a confluence of people ſeene in that countrey: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the nouelty, many forraine Princes came to celebrate this mariage, and to ſhew their owne greatnes. <hi>Sauoy</hi> was neare, and ſent ſome from her ſnowie hills: <hi>France</hi> as neare, and ſent others from her fruitfull vines: <hi>Italy</hi> not far off, and ſent many from her pleaſant fields: and the Ilands round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout kept none at home that would come. Thus were his kinred inuited, ſtrangers admitted, his owne people entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and all ſorts welcommed: but as yet no bride was ſeene, no woman named, no lady deſigned, no maid publiſhed, no wife knowne: onely the preparation was much, and the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation greater.</p>
               <p>All this while the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> continued his hunting; and as he had accuſtomed, reſorted much to a poore country village not farre from <hi>Saluſſe;</hi> where there dwelt as poore a countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, named <hi>Ianicole,</hi> ouerworne in yeares, and ouercomne with diſtreſſe. But as it happens many times, that inward graces doe moderate outward diſcommodities, and that God ſeaſoneth pouerty with contentment and their ſufficient ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation: ſo had this poore man all his deſerts ſupplied in the admirable comfort of one onely daughter; ſo compoſed, as if Nature determined a worke of oſtentation. For ſuch was her
<pb facs="tcp:19585:4"/> beauty in appearance, and vertue in operation, that it put iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious men to an extaſie in the choiſe by compariſon: but both vnited did héere grace each other; and when they pretended an action, it was all to go forward to perfection. And whereas in others this temporary bleſſing gaue wings to deſire, to bee ſeene and knowne abroad; in her thoſe innated vertues allaied the heat of all manner of paſſion, and breakings out of frailty. The viands they had were but meane, and the diet they kept was to ſatisfie nature: the time was ouer-ruled by their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks, and the ceremonies they vſed were thanks to God, &amp; moderation in their repaſts. The vtenſiles of the houſe were homely, yet handſome in regard of their cleanlineſſe: that bed which they had the ould man lay in, and the ſwéet daug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> made ſhift with the ground. No day paſſed without pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> and praiſes to God (for was it not praiſe-worthy to ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch grace in this diſgrace?) nor any night, without taking account of the day paſſed. Her exerciſe was to helpe her father in the morning, and driue forth her ſheep in the day time: hée was at home making of nets, and ſhee abroad looking to her lambs: ſhe was neuer heard to wiſh for any better, but to thank God it was no worſe. No word of repining euer came from her mouth, or the leaſt grudge from her heart: at night ſhe folded her ſheep, and dreſſed her fathers ſupper: then lay they downe to reſt, and reſted as well as in a bed of Downe indeed. This was the glory of their pouerty, and memory of their content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>But as fire will not be hid where there is matter comhuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: ſo vertue will not be obſcured where there be tongues and eares: nor could the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> ſo hallow after his hawks and hounds, but report hallowed in his eare, as faſt, this wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; inſomuch that when it was confirmed by iudicious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, he made it not dainty to be behoulding to his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. Which when he ſaw concurring with fame, the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle brought a kinde of aſtoniſhment: which continuing the properties of ſuch nouelties, increaſed to meditation: and ſo comparing the reſt with this rarity, he thought her a fit woman to make his wife; ſuppoſing that if ſhe were vertuous by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="tcp:19585:5"/> ſhe could not proue vicious by education: but rather as a diamond is a ſtone of the ſame value, whether ſet in lead or horne, it muſt needs bee of more excellency embelliſhed with gold and enamell. In which reſolution hee prepared his heart, and went forward with his buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>In the meane time the Court was daintily furniſhed, the plate prepared, the apparell magnificent, the coronet rich, the iewels precious, the ornaments excéeding, and all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting the magnificence of a prince, &amp; the dignitie of a queen: only the Nobles wondred, the ladies were amazed, the damſels maruelled, the Gentles diſputed, the people flocked, and all ſorts attended to ſée who ſhould poſſeſſe this wealth, and bée adorned with theſe robes. Till at laſt the nuptial day came indeed: honour prepared the ſumptuouſnes: fame diuulged the glory: <hi>Hymen</hi> inuited the gueſts: magnificence adorned the roomes: the Officers marſhald the State: and all loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for a Bride: but who ſhe was, the next Chapter muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. How after all this great preparation, the Marqueſſe of Saluſs demanded <hi>Griſell</hi> of her poore father <hi>Ianicola;</hi> and eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her, made her Marchioneſſe of Saluſs.</head>
               <p>WHen all things were extended to this glorious ſhew, the Marqueſſe (as if he went to fetch his wife indeed) tooke with him a great company of Earls, Lords, Knights, Squires and Gentlemen, Ladies and attendants; and went from the Palace into the Country toward <hi>Ianicolas</hi> houſe; where the faire mayd <hi>Griſel</hi> knowing nothing of that which hapned, nor once dreaming of that which was to come, had made her houſe and ſelfe ſomwhat handſome, determining (with the reſt of her neighbor Virgins) to ſée this ſolemnity: at which inſtant arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Marqueſſe with all his gracious company, meeting with <hi>Griſel,</hi> as ſhée was carrying two pitchers of water to her poor fathers houſe. Of whom (calling her by her name) he as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, where her father was: ſhe humbly anſwered, in the houſe.
<pb facs="tcp:19585:5"/> Goe then ſaid hee, and tell him I would ſpeak with him. So the poore old man (made the poorer by this aſtoniſhment) came forth to the Lord ſomewhat appauled: till the <hi>Marqueſſe,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him by the hand, with an extraordinary chearefulneſſe, ſaid, that he had a ſecret to impart vnto him; and ſo ſequeſtring him from the company, ſpake theſe words: <hi>Ianicola,</hi> I know, that you alwaies loued me, and am reſolued, that you doe not now hate me: you haue beene glad when I haue been pleaſed; and will not now bee ſorrowfull, if I bee ſatisfied: nay, I am ſure, if it lie in your power, you will further my delight, and not bee a contrary to my requeſt. For I intend to begge your daughter for my wife, and bee your ſonne in lawe for your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement. What ſaieſt thou man? wilt thou accept mee for a friend, as I haue appointed thee for a father? The poore ould man was ſo aſtoniſhed, that he could not looke vp for teares, nor ſpeake a word for ioy: but when the extaſie had end, hee thus faintly replied; My gracious Soueraigne, you are my lord, and therefore I muſt accord to your will; but you are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous, and therefore I preſume on your vertue: take her a Gods name, and make mee a glad father; and let that God, which raiſeth the humble and méek, make her a befitting wife, and fruitfull mother. Why then, replied the <hi>Marqueſſe,</hi> let vs enter your houſe: for I muſt aske her a queſtion before you. So hee went in, the company tarrying without in great aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: the faire maid was buſied to make it as handſome as ſhe could; and proud againe, to haue ſuch a gueſt vnder her roofe; amazed at nothing, but why hee ſhould come ſo accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied, and little coniecturing of ſo great a bleſſing approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. But at laſt, the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> took her by the hand, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed theſe ſpéeches: To tel you this bluſh becomes you, it were but a folly; and that your modeſty hath graced your comelines, may proue the deceit of words, and vnbefitting my greatnes: but in a word, your father and I haue agreed to make you my wife, and I hope you will not diſagree to take me to your huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. For delay ſhall not intangle you with ſuſpicion, nor two daies longer protract the kindnes: onely I muſt bee ſatisfied in this, if your heart affoord a willing entertainement to the
<pb facs="tcp:19585:6"/> motion; and your vertue a conſtancy to this reſolution, Not to repine at my pleaſure in any thing, nor preſume on contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when I determine to command. For as amongſt good ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, they muſt ſimply obey without diſputing the buſineſſe: ſo muſt vertuous wiues dutifully conſent without reproofe, or the leaſt contraction of a brow. Therefore be aduiſed how you anſwer, and I charge you take heed, that the tongue vtter no more then the heart conceits. All this while was <hi>Griſel</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring at the miracle, had not religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> told her, that nothing was impoſſible to the Commander of all things; which reduced her to a better conſideration, and thus brought forth an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere:</p>
               <p>My gracious lord, I am not ignorant of your greatneſſe, and know mine owne baſeneſſe; there is no worth in me to be your ſeruant, therefore there can be no deſert to be your wife: notwithſtanding, becauſe God will be the Author of miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous accidents, I yéeld to your pleaſure, and praiſe him for the fortune, onely this I will be bold to ſay, That your will ſhall ſhall be my delight, and death ſhall be more welcome vnto mée, then a word of diſpleaſure againſt you.</p>
               <p>This is ſufficient, anſwered the great lord, and ſo moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly he took her by the hand, and brought her to the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, euen before all his peeres and great ladies; and told them, ſhee ſhould bee his wife: ſo that wherein they extended their loue, reuerence, and obedience toward her, he would exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his regard, care, and diligence toward them. And becauſe outward ſhewes doe ſometimes grace befitting actions (leſt her pouerty and baſenes might too much daunt their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſeeme diſgratious to their noblenes) he commanded them with a morall liuelineſſe to adorne her with the richeſt robes they had: ſo that it was a pleaſure to ſee, how the ladies beſtire themſelues; a delight, to behould the ſeuerall ſeruices performed; the many hands about her; the iewels and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, the robes and mantles; the ornaments and coronets; the <hi>collanaes</hi> and chaines; with all other particulars and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couterements: but when ſhe was apparelled indeed, it was a rauiſhment excéeding report, and they which ſtomached her
<pb facs="tcp:19585:6"/> preferment, were now delighted with her glory. Such a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit hath beauty by nature, and gratiouſneſſe by nurture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. How the Marqueſſe and <hi>Griſel</hi> were married together.</head>
               <p>AFter the ladies had thus adorned poore <hi>Griſel</hi> with robes befitting her eſtate, the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> and all the noble com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany returned to <hi>Saluſs,</hi> and in the Cathedrall Church in ſight of the people, according to the fulneſſe of religious ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, they were eſpouſed together, and with great ſolemnitie returned to the palace. Herein yet conſiſted the admiration, that no word of reproach was murmured, nor eie looked vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſantly vpon her: for by her wonderfull demeanour ſhee had gained ſo much of opinion, that the baſenes of her birth was not thought vpon, and all her graces concurring made them verely beleeue, ſhee was extracted of princely lineage: no man once ſuppoſed, that ſhee could bee <hi>Griſel,</hi> daughter to poore <hi>Ianicola;</hi> but rather ſome creature metamorphoſed by the powers of heauen: for beſides the outward ſtatelineſſe &amp; maieſticall carriage of herſelfe, the wonderfull modeſtie and exact ſymmetry of her countenance, the admirable beauty and extraordinary fauor of her viſage, her faire demeanour had a kinde of attraction, and her gratious words, a ſwéet deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; ſo that all that came to her were glad of their acceſſe, and they which went from her, triumphed for their good ſpéed: yea, report extended ſo far, that ſhe was not onely viſited by her owne lords and ladies with reuerence; but attended on with ſtrangers, who came from all quarters to ſée her, and to bée behoulding to their owne iudgements: ſo that if the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe</hi> loued her before for her owne worth, he now reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced her for others reſpect; the rather, becauſe he found a ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſing attending her preſence, and all people pleaſed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. For when any controuerſie hapned betwéene himſelfe and his Nobles, ſhe was ſo nobly minded, that what ſhe could not obtaine by faire intreaty, ſhe yet mitigated by ſwéet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion. When any vnkindnes hapned of forraine Princes,
<pb facs="tcp:19585:7"/> ſhée vrged thoſe bleſſings of peace, and reaſoned the matter with delightſom enforcement &amp; when the people were either complained of, or againſt, he maruelled from whence ſhe had thoſe pretty reaſons to aſſwage his anger, and they verely beléeued ſhee was ſent from heauen for their reléefe. Thus was ſhée amiable to her lord, acceptable to her people, profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to her Country, a mirror of her Sexe, a perſon priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by nature, and a wonder of the time, in which ſhe did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of time; ſo that the Marqueſſe was rather rauiſhed then louing, and all his ſubiects reſolued to obedience from her good example.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. How the Lady <hi>Griſel</hi> was proued by her Husband, who thus made triall of her patience.</head>
               <p>TO other bleſſings, in proceſſe of time, there was added the birth of a ſwéet Infant, a Daughter, that reioiced the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and gladded the father; the Country triumphed, and the people clapped their hands for ioy. For the Marqueſſe ſtill lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued her more and more, and they thought their liues not déere for her, if occaſion ſerued. Notwithſtanding all this, Fortune hath ſtill a tricke to checke the pride of life, and proſperity muſt be ſeaſoned with ſome croſſes, or elſe it would taint &amp; corrupt vs too much. Whereupon, the Marqueſſe determined now to proue his wife, and make triall of her vertues indeed: and ſo taking a conuenient ſeaſon, after the childe was fully meaned, he one day repaired ſecretly to her chamber, and (ſéeming halfe angry) thus imparted his mind:</p>
               <p>Although, <hi>Griſel,</hi> this your preſent Fortune hath made you forget your former eſtate, and that the iollity of your life ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwayeth the remembrance of your birth; yet, neither is it ſo with me, nor my Nobles: For I haue ſome occaſion of diſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and they great cauſe of repining, in that they muſt be ſubiect to one ſo baſe, and haue ſtill before their eyes our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſuch low degrée; ſo that though (for my ſake) they make good ſemblance of the preſent, yet are they reſolued neuer to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="tcp:19585:7"/> any of our poſterity to rule ouer them; of which, as they haue diſputed with mee, I cannot chuſe but forewarne you: Therefore, to preuent this diſcontentment betwéene vs, and to maintaine that peace which muſt corroborate my eſtate, I muſt néedes yeelde to their iudgements, and take away your Daughter from you, to preſerue their amity: the thing I know muſt be diſpleaſing to Nature, and a Mother cannot well indure ſuch a loſſe: but there is now no remedy, only make vſe of your firſt reſolutions, and remember what you promiſed me at the beginning of our Contract.</p>
               <p>The Lady hearing this ſorrowfull preamble, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the Marqueſſe reſolution, to her griefe (although eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry word might haue béene as arrowes in her ſides) yet admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the temptation, and diſputing with her ſelfe to what end the vertues of Patience, Modeſty, Forbearance, Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Magnanimity were ordained, if they had not ſubiects to worke vpon, and obiects to looke after; thus replyed:</p>
               <p>My lord, you are my Soueraigne, and all earthly pleaſures and contentments of my life come from you, as the fountaine of my happineſſe; and therefore pleaſe your ſelfe, and (beléeue it) it is my pleaſure that you are pleaſed: as for the child, it is the gift of God and yours. Now he that giues may take away, and as wée receiue bleſſings from heauen, ſo muſt we not dote on them on earth; leſt by ſetting our minds too much vpon them, wée cannot ſet off our hearts when they are taken from vs: only one thing I deſire, that you remember I am a mother, and if I burſt not out into paſſion for her loſſe, it is for your ſake I am no more perplexed, and ſo you ſhall euer find mee a wife befitting your deſires.</p>
               <p>When the Marqueſſe ſaw her conſtancy, and was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner pleaſed with her modeſt anſwere, hée replied not at all at that time. For his heart was full, and what betweene ioy and feare he departed: ioy that ſo great vertue had the increaſe of goodneſſe: feare that he had preſumed too farre on ſuch a trial: but reſolued in his buſineſſe, hee went to put it to the aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19585:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. The Marqueſſe ſent a Varlet for his daughter; but priuatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of her with his ſiſter, the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Bologna de grace,</hi> who brought her vp in all things befitting the childe of ſo great a perſon.</head>
               <p>NOt long after this ſad conference betwéen the Marqueſſe and his lady, hée called a faithfull ſeruant vnto him; ſuch a one as the poet talks of, <hi>propter fidem &amp; taciturnitatem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectum,</hi> to whom hée imparts this ſecrecy; and with ſeuerall inſtructions, what hée truly meant to do with the child, ſent him to his wife with an vnſauory meſſage; which yet hée de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered in this manner:</p>
               <p>I had not now come to you, moſt noble lady, though that power commanded me, which hath my life in ſubiection, if I had not more relied vpon your wiſdome and vertue, than fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red death it ſelfe. Therefore I craue pardon if I am diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in my meſſage, and ſéeme cruell (as it were) in tearing your fleſh from your ſides, by bereauing you of this your daughter: for hée hath appointed it that muſt not bée gainſaid, and I am a meſſenger that cannot bée denied: but yet with what vnwillingnes (God knowes my ſoule.) in regard that you are ſo reſpected amongſt vs, that wée think of nothing but what may delight you, and talk not a word, but of your merit and worthineſſe!</p>
               <p>When ſhée had heard him out; remembring the conference the Marqueſſe had with her, and apprehending there was no diſputing in a matter remedileſſe, eſpecially with a meſſenger, ſhée reſolued it was ordained to dy: and although ſhée muſt now (as it were) commit it to a ſlaughter-houſe, whereby a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny woman in the world might with good becomming haue burſt out into ſome paſſion, and well enough ſhewed a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted extaſie; yet recollecting her ſpirits, and reclaiming thoſe motiues of nature already ſtriuing in her bowels, ſhée took the childe in her armes, and with a mothers bleſſing, and
<pb facs="tcp:19585:8"/> ſwéetned kiſſes, the countenance ſomewhat ſad, and the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture without any violent excruciation, deliuered it vnto the fellow, not once amazed nor diſtempred, becauſe her lord would haue it ſo, and ſhée knew not how to haue it otherwiſe: only ſhee ſaid, I muſt, my friend, intreat one thing at your hands, that out of humanity and Chriſtian obſeruation, you leaue not the body to bée deuoured of beaſts or birds: for it is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of a graue in her innocency: and Chriſtian buriall, though ſhée were but my daughter alone.</p>
               <p>The fellow hauing receiued the childe, durſt not tarry for feare of diſcouery (ſuch impreſſion had her words make alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) but returned with it to his Maiſter; not leauing out the leaſt circumſtance of her anſwer, nor any thing might enlarge her renowne and conſtancy.</p>
               <p>The Marqueſſe conſidering the great vertue of his wife, and looking on the beauty of his daughter, began to enter into a kinde of compaſſion, and to retract his wilfulneſſe: but at laſt, reſolution won the field of pity and hauing (as he thought) ſo well begunne, would not ſo ſoone giue ouer: but with the ſame ſecrecy hée had taken her from his wife, hée ſent it away to his ſiſter, the Ducheſs of <hi>Bologna,</hi> with preſents of worth, and letters of gratification, containing in them the nature of the buſineſſe, and the manner of her bringing vp; which ſhee accordingly put in practice, receiuing her néece with ioy, and inſtructing her with diligence: ſo that it ſoone appeared, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what a tutelage ſhée was, and whoſe daughter ſhee might be. For her pregnancy learned whatſoeuer they taught her: and the grace ſhee added, quickly diſcouered, that honour had confederated with nature to make her the of-ſpring of ſuch a mother.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19585:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. The Marqueſſe, not contented with this proofe, tooke away alſo her ſonne, in which aduerſity (with other additions) ſhe ſhewed an extraordinary patience.</head>
               <p>AFter this tempeſt was ouerpaſt, the rage whereof might eaſily haue broken the tender ſides of poore <hi>Griſels</hi> Barke (For, ſhée verely beleeued that her Daughter was ſlaine) the Marqueſſe ſtill lay in waite for the trial of his wife, watching euery opportunity which might acquaint him with her diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments; eſpecially, if he might vnderſtand whether ſhée complained of his rigorouſneſſe and vnkindneſſe, or no: but when he not onely was aduertiſed of her conſtancy, and faire demeanor, but ſaw (by experience) that ſhée was neither ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in proſperity, nor deiected in aduerſity: when hee percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo great a temperature betwéene the ioy of her aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the ſorrow for her trouble, hée wondred at her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy; and the rather, becauſe her loue and obſeruation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him continued with that ſwéetnes, and had ſuch delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble paſſages, that his heart was ſet on fire againe, and hee knew not how to allay the extreamities of his ioy. In this manner paſſed foure yéeres, wherein ſhée ouerpaſſed all of her kinde; and he thought it a donatiue from heauen to haue ſuch a wife. At laſt, nature beſtird herſelfe againe, and made her a happy mother of a faire ſonne; the ioy whereof led the whole Country into the houſe of praier &amp; thankſgiuing, and brought them home againe by creſſet-light and bonfires: ſo that ſhée well perceiued how acceptable ſhée was to her people, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of her husband. Notwithſtanding, with the ſame water that draue the mill, hée drowned it; and made her ſtill beléeue the contrary: for after two yéeres, that the childe was paſt the danger of a cradle, and the trouble of infancy, hée took occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on once againe to inflict vpon the vertuous <hi>Griſel</hi> a new pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; erecting his building vpon the old foundation. You knowe, ſaith hée, what former contentions I haue had with my Nobility about our marriage, not that they can lay any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
<pb facs="tcp:19585:9"/> on you or your worthy behauior, but on my fortune and diſaſterous affection to match my ſelfe ſo meanly: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in yet their forward exprobration was rebated, all the while we either had no children, or that they ſuppoſed, that which we had to be taken from vs: all which ariſeth out of the error of ambition (which, in a manner, is careleſſe of vertue) reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting nothing but a high Progeny: ſo that euer ſince this child was borne, there hath paſſed many ſecret grudgings, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde ſpeeches againſt it, as if it were a diſparagement to their greatneſſe, to haue a lord of ſo meane Parentage, and the Country to be ſubiect to the grand child of <hi>Ianicola,</hi> whom you ſée, neuer ſince our mariage, they would admit to place of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, or to ouertop them by way of aſſociation; nor will ſuffer this my <hi>Gualter,</hi> though it carry the fathers name to rule ouer them. Therefore, to allay the heat of theſe preſent fires, &amp; to preſerue the peace of my eſtate (by preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting the miſchief of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture troubles) I am reſolued to ſettle my contentment, and to deale with your ſonne, as I haue dealt with your daughter. And of this I thought good to aduertiſe you, as a preparatiue for patience, leſt ſorrow ſhould diſtract with ouerſuddenneſſe.</p>
               <p>Now you Ladies and Dames of theſe times, that ſtand vpon tearmes of ſpirit and greatneſſe of heart (ſome will haue it courage and magnanimity of minde) that are affrighted at the Character of a foole: and ſilly poore ſoule, I ſpeake not of Strumpets, or of ſuch as are willing to brand themſelues with the impurity of vncleanneſſe, and dare out of impudency or running, tell their Huſbands to their faces, they will goe where they liſt, and do what they pleaſe; but of ſuch that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that impregnable target of honeſtie are yet ſo impatient at euery diſtemperature, that they dare anſwere taunt for taunt: yea like <hi>Viragos</hi> indeed offer the firſt blow, though a horrible confuſion follow; what would you haue anſwered this lord? or with what fire-works would you haue made your approches vnto him? I will not tarry for your anſwere, leſt I pull the old houſe in peeces, and ſo though I ſcape the timber I may be cruſhed with the rubbiſh: but I will now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> all obiections. In telling you what
<pb facs="tcp:19585:10"/> faire <hi>GRISEL</hi> ſaid: and if there bée hope of reformation, inſert it as a caution, to diuert you from your naturall fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
               <p>When ſhée had heard him out: though to the griefe of her ſoule, ſhée conceiued the murther of her childe, and that the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion renewed the ſorrow of her daughters loſſe: yet would ſhée giue no way to ſuch diſtemperature, that either hée ſhould haue cauſe to ſuſpect her patience, or ſhée herſelfe the temptation of diſquiet; and therefore thus replied: My lord, I haue many times told you, that my ſoule reioiceth in nothing but in your repoſednes: for you are the lord of mée and this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant: and though I could bée contented to ſhew my ſelfe a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his education, and bring him now and then vnto you as the pledge of our loues, yet are you the commander of my vowes, and I will rectifie all diſordered appetites by the rule of your pleaſure. Take him then a Gods name, and if hée bée marked for death, it is but the common brand of all creatures; nay, if the mother may bée a ſacrifice of propitiation to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe your diſquiet, neuer was lamb ſo meek, nor holocauſt ſo willing to bée offred. For, what may bée comprehended vnder the titles of father, kinred, children, friends, life, pleaſure, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and contentment, are all compriſed vnder your loue, and the ſociety of a husband. Do with mée then what you pleaſe: the body ſhall ſerue your turne while it liues, and the ſoule at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend you after death.</p>
               <p>Héere was an anſwer to pacifie the tyrants of <hi>Sicilie,</hi> and put a man quite out of his tract of prouing ſuch a wife: yet the Marqueſſe onely made vſe of it to reioice in the aſſurance of her goodnes; and went the rather forward in his dangerous courſe of temptation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19585:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. The Marqueſſe, reſolute to proue his wife further, ſendeth for his ſon, &amp; diſpoſeth of him as he had done of his daughter.</head>
               <p>AS this patient and wonderfull lady was one day ſporting with her infant; like an vntimely tempeſt (ſpoiling the beauty of ſome new rooted plants) did this meſſenger of death interpoſe himſelfe betwéene her recreation, making the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low demand of her ſonne worſe than the noiſe of aſchrich-owle ouer a ſick mans bed: yet (as if there were a conſcience in diſquieting her greatnes, or if you will, her goodnes) he came forward with preambles and apologies, inſinuating with cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing pardon the authority of a lord, the duty of a ſeruant, the terrour of death, the circumſtance of obedience, and all other enforcements which might either excuſe a meſſenger, or make the meſſage it ſelfe without blame. What ſhould I enlarge a diſcourſe of terrour? it is a curteſie to conclude a miſchiefe with quicknes: hée was not ſo ſudden in his demand, as ſhée was ready in her diſpatch: for ſhe preſently bleſt the child, kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, croſſed it, adorned it, and deliuered it to the executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: onely with the ſame enforcement ſhée pleaded, as ſhée had ſpoken of in the behalfe of her daughter; not to ſée it periſh for lack of a buriall, or deuoured for want of a graue.</p>
               <p>In this manner, and with this report hée returned to his lord, who had ſtill more cauſe of amazement, and leſſe reaſon to trouble ſuch a creature, had not his wilfulnes put him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to make an end of his buſineſſe, and taught him ſtill vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of trying this gold in the fire. But for the time, hée ſent likewiſe this childe to his ſiſter, the Ducheſſe of <hi>Bologna</hi> (yet ſome will haue her but Counteſſe of <hi>Paniche</hi>) who, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding her brothers minde, brought vp both theſe children in ſuch a faſhion, that though no man knew whoſe children they were, yet they imagined whoſe they might bée; that is, the ſon and daughter of ſome prince, or other potentate, willing to haue his children brought vp to the beſt purpoſe, and befitting their birth and honour.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19585:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19585:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19585:12"/>
               <p>The ordering of this buſineſſe in this ſort, made the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe once againe ſettle himſelfe in <hi>Saluſs,</hi> where hée kept o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen houſe to all comers; and was proud of nothing ſo much, as the honour of his wife, and the loue of his people: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had thus tried her patience and conſtancy, giuing her more then ſufficient cauſe of anguiſh and perturbation, yet could he not finde fault, or had the leaſt demonſtration of offence, but ſtill ſhe loued him more and more, and was ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruingly dutifull, and cautelous of diſpleaſure, that many times he grew enamored of that he might command, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med paſſionate in the diſtractions of ouer-ioy. Nor could the length of time make this loue weariſome, for all they had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thus a doſen yeares together: onely ſhee got the hand of him in the opinion of the people, who by this time beganne to whiſper againſt his vnkindnes, that had married ſo vertuous a woman, &amp; bereaued her of two children, ſo that if they were ſlaine, it was a murther, if otherwiſe, it was vnkindneſſe. For though ſhee were poore <hi>Ianicolas</hi> daughter by birth, yet ſhe might come from heauen for her vertue, and was ſure to go thither for her piety. Notwithſtanding theſe breakings out, which came often to the eares of his honour, ſuch was her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and his gouernment, that they only whiſperd the ſame in her behalfe, and contented themſelues with the expectation of future good, as they had the fruition of preſent happineſſe; not meddling with the ſame further, then in the commiſerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her, and ſtill acknowledging their duty to him: ſo that although hee knew ſhee might this way vnderſtand his former reaſons of taking away her children, that it was but a deuice, and that there were ſome other motiues, which procured this vnkindnes: yet was hee ſtill obſtinate to exerciſe her patience, and conceit beat out another plot of offence on the anuill of a louing, yet moſt hardned heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19585:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. The Marqueſſe, to try his Lady further, made her beleeue hee would marry another wife.</head>
               <p>SOme doſen yéeres were paſſed, ſince the Marqueſſe of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſs</hi> had ſent his daughter to <hi>Bologna</hi> to his ſiſter (as you haue heard) who was by this time growne to that beautie, comelineſſe and perfection, that her fame buſied all <hi>Europe;</hi> and the lady <hi>Griſel,</hi> her Mother, was made acquainted with her excellency; whereupon, he very ſtrangely ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> by a Meſſenger of truſt, for counterfait letters to marrie his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon, and to bee diſpenſed from his firſt wife. Which was ſo effectually diſpatched, that the Meſſenger ſoone returned with the approbation of his requeſt, and hee himſelfe had many allegations in readineſſe to excuſe the matter, intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the good of the Countrie, and the continuall deſire of his people for the alteration; which although it was far from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, becauſe they pitied their ladies diſtreſſe, and rather repined againſt their lords vnconſtancy: yet it ſerued his turne for the time, and he thereupon erected the frame of this ſecond marriage. By this time is the faire <hi>Griſel</hi> acquainted with the buſineſſe, and troubled at the misfortune; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing many times plaied the wanton with affliction, ſhe reſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled herſelfe to endure whatſoeuer ſhould be impoſed: ſo that when ſhe came to the proofe indéed, nothing affronted her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, nor humbled her lower, then her own vertue had taught her the way.</p>
               <p>In the meane while the Marqueſſe had vnder hand ſent to the Count of <hi>Paniche,</hi> and his ſiſter, to bring him his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with all the pompe and glory they could prepare; with caution, not to diſcouer their names and to be at a day appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Saluſs:</hi> ſo that it paſſed for currant all ouer the Country, that a lady, a yong, braue, and gallant lady, of great lineage,
<pb facs="tcp:19585:13"/> and greater worth, of high renown and mighty affinity, was comming into <hi>Saluſs</hi> to be eſpouſed to the Marqueſſe, and that they were already come out of <hi>Bologna de Grace,</hi> a whole dayes iourney forward, with ſuch a troope and company, that it was a ſhew of magnificence, and a ſpectacle of delight. For amongſt the reſt, there was a young lord, not fully eight yéere old, whoſe brauery and gallantneſſe drew all mens eyes with admiration toward him, had not the lady diuided the gazing, and ſhared with their opinion. For, beſides her riches and outward ornaments, her youth (as not fully thirtéene) and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right comelineſſe, her bewty and gracious behauiour, ſhe was of extraordinary ſtature and maieſtike preſence.</p>
               <p>Theſe things thus diſpoſed and handſomly carried, the Marqueſſe tooke an opportunity thus to ſpeak to the diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <hi>Griſel</hi> before all his people: In times paſt I confeſſe you deſerued my loue, and notwithſtanding the diſparity betwéene vs, I thought it well beſtowed vpon you; nay, I cannot now impute any ill deſert vnto you: notwithſtanding, for ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to my ſelfe beſt knowne, of which I haue made the holy Father acquainted, I am reſolued to take another wife; who, as you heare, is on the way hitherward already: therefore I would aduiſe you to retire to your fathers cotage, till you heare further from me.</p>
               <p>Alas my lord, replied the ſwéet ſoule, I euer diſputed the matter with reaſon, that there was no equality betwéene ſo great magnificence and my humiliation, and in the greateſt aſſurance of my proſperity, replaced my ſelfe a vaſſaile &amp; hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid; proud of nothing but my owne readineſſe to be at your command, &amp; your willingnes to imploy mee in your affaires; ſo that I take God to my witnes, I ſcarce truſted my ſelfe with the name of a wife, when I was in the beſt aſſurance. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I muſt acknowledge, what you haue heeretofore vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed, as a part of great bounty, and the very fruits of your generouſnes. As for returning to my poore Fathers houſe, I am moſt willing; and there as you pleaſe, like a forlorne wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow wil ſpend the reſt of my dayes: yet remember I was your wife, eſpouſed orderly, and you haue had children by mee, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:19585:13"/> that if I there dye, I muſt yet dye the widdow of ſuch a lord, and for honors ſake be ſo reputed. As for your new Spouſe, God grant her many daies of comfort, and you many yeeres of ioy, that you may liue in reciprocall delight one with another, and intertaine no worſe contentment, then poore <hi>Griſel</hi> accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. As for my Dowry I brought, I brought only my ſelfe, and will haue no more backe againe, which was, faith, loue, reuerence, pouerty and virginity: For, as I came naked from my fathers houſe, I am contented to returne ſo againe. Your iewels are in the wardrobe, and euen the ring you married mée withal, in the Chambex: of this I weare I ſhall quickly be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robed, and if there be any further miſery appointed, my pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can endure it, if your pleaſure impoſe it; onely in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of my Virginitie, I requeſt a poore ſmocke to hide that wombe from publicke ouerlooking, that was once ſo priuate to ſo great a Prince: and becauſe it was the bed of your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, let it not bee the ſtorne of your people, but giue mee leaue thus to goe out of the Palace, that hereafter times may wonder, how quietly a woman yéelded to ſo great a change. Nay, let no man ſhed a teare, I muſt bée more naked then ſo: for though the wife of a Marqueſſe while I liued, and the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow when I died, yet am I not too good for a graue, but in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of pride muſt returne to duſt and aſhes.</p>
               <p>Did I ſay before, they beganne to wéep? I can aſſure you, when ſhée had done, they roared out-right; yea, the Marqueſſe himſelfe ſhed ſo many teares, that he was faine to retire; and commanded the ſmock ſhée had begged to be ſent vnto her, that ſhée might proſecute the enterpriſe, and he determine his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as he had conſtantly proiected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. How the patient <hi>Griſel</hi> was diſrobed of her apparell, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all that ſhe had (except one poore ſmocke) to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe.</head>
               <p>BEfore I procéed any further in this wonderfull diſcouery, I am ſure two things will bee obiected againſt mée: firſt,
<pb facs="tcp:19585:14"/> the impoſſibility of the ſtory; ſecondly, the abſurdity of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſtory I anſwer, that therefore it was thus pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and connected together, for the rarity of the buſineſſe, and the ſwéetnes of the ſucceſſe; nor is it any way ſtranger than many Roman paſſages, and Gretian diſcourſes. For the application, it is both neceſſary and befitting: for whereas in the condition of women, amongſt many other there bée two eſpeciall errours againſt the modeſty of their ſex, and quietnes of their husbands, <hi>videlicet,</hi> ſuperiority, and deſire of liberty (I name not irregular behauiour, houſhould inconueniences, and domeſticks ſtrife) this one example (as <hi>Hercules</hi> did the ſerpents) ſtrangles them both in the cradle: and though it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not preuent, yet will it exprobrate the fault. Firſt concerning ſuperiority, I hope the inſtances of Scripture are not made Canonicall to no purpoſe: and out of reaſon and naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement, what a filthineſſe is it to a generous ſpirit, to haue a woman ſo preſumptuous as to take an account of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands actions and buſineſſe? wherein many times they are ſo peremptory, that I haue ſéene them enter into the roome of priuacy, where ſecret buſineſſes of ſtrangers haue been impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and were to be diſcuſſed, nor hath this been done with a louely inſinuation, or cunning excuſe of longing, or willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be inſtructed, or other pretty inducements to permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but with a high commanding voice, and impudent aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their owne worth: yea, I haue knowne them breake o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen letters before they came to their husbands ouerlooking, and haue wondred euen at ſouldiers themſelues, that would giue way to ſuch vndecency. Againe, to be counterchecked in this wilfulnes, what clamours haue béene raiſed? what tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and diſcomforts occaſioned? that inſtead of awfull o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and delightſome affability, they haue burſt out into outragiouſnes, commanded teares of miſchiefe, and threatned ſuſpicions reuenges: but let them ſoile themſelues in the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of this humour neuer ſo much, I ſay plainely, that though their husbands were fooles by nature, yet is it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting for a wife to diſcouer the ſame, or ouer-rule in forren affaires, I meane matters which concerne them not: for there
<pb facs="tcp:19585:14"/> is no great man ſo weake, but hath councell and ſupportation of inferior Officers; nor mean man ſo ſottiſh, but hath friends or ſeruants in the diſpatch of his buſineſſe. Secondly, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the deſire of liberty; oh helliſh deuice of the diuell, and fearefull cuſtome both of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England!</hi> I hope he that knowes the faſhions of the Eaſt, of <hi>Muſcouy, Spaine, Italy,</hi> and the Mores, vnderſtands, that no married wife goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad but to honorable purpoſes; and it is an introduction to death, to ſalute any ſtranger, or be ſéene in priuate conference. For, in true vnderſtanding, what buſineſſe ſhould any man haue with my wife thrée houres together in priuate? or why, without my leaue, and that vpon good grounds, ſhould ſhee wander in publike. I ſpeake not to ouerthrow noble ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, generous intertainment, familiar inuitations, curteous behauiour, charitable welcomes, honeſt recreations, or perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture, the imparting of priuate buſineſſe: but méerly againſt foppiſh wantonneſſe, idle talke, ſuſpicions méetings, damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble play-hunting, diſorderly gaming, vnbefitting exerciſes; and in a word, all ſuch things as tend to obſcenity and wickednes; in which (ſay what women can) if there be not a moderation, by nature, there muſt bee an inforcement by iudgement: and that woman that will not be ruled by good councell, muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerruled by better example. Of which, this now in hand (of lady <hi>Griſel</hi>) is a mirror, and tranſparent Cryſtall to manifeſt true vertue, and wifely duty indéed, and ſo I come to the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of her obedience.</p>
               <p>After the Marqueſſe was reſolued to the laſt Act of her try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and had ſent her the ſmocke ſhée demanded, amongſt all the Lords, Knights, Ladies and other company, ſhe preſently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robed her ſelfe, and went ſo accompanied, from the Palace, to her fathers Cottage, who as you haue heard (for diuers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) was only kept from want, but neuer aduanced out of the ſame.</p>
               <p>The company could not chooſe but wéepe and deplore the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Fortune: ſhe could not chooſe but ſmile, that her vertue was predominant ouer paſſion: they exclaimed againſt the cruelty of her lord, ſhe diſclaimed the leaſt inuentiue againſt
<pb facs="tcp:19585:15"/> him: they wondred at ſo great vertue and patience, ſhe reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them they were exerciſes befitting a modeſt woman; they followed her with true loue and deſires to doe her good, ſhee thanked them with a true heart, and requeſt to deſiſt from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further deploring of her eſtate.</p>
               <p>By this time they approched the houſe, and the poore old man <hi>Ianicola</hi> acquainted with the hurliburly, came out to ſée what the matter was. And finding it was his daughter in her ſmocke, and in ſo honourable a company, bemoaning het di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, ſhe quickly left them all vnſpoke vnto, and ran in for thoſe poore robes, which were formerly left in the houſe: with which hee quickly arayed her, and told her before them all, that now ſhée was in her right element; and kiſſing her, bad her welcom. The company was as much aſtoniſhed at his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, as at her conſtancie, wondring how nature could bee ſo reſtrained from paſſion, and that any woman had ſuch grace to be ſo gracious; in which amaze, not without ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of fortune, and their Lords cruelty, they left her to the pouerty of the Cell, and returnrd themſelues to the glory of the Palace: where they recounted to the Marqueſſe, the ſtrangeneſſe of the buſineſſe, and the manner of the accidents, and ſhee continued in her firſt moderation and indefatigable patience; the poore Father onely laughing to ſcorne the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and ſodaine mutabilitie of humane condition, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting his daughter in her well-begun courſes of modeſty and repoſedneſſe.</p>
               <p>Not long after, approched the Counteſſe of <hi>Paniche,</hi> or if you will Ducheſſe of <hi>Bologna,</hi> with her glorious company and beautifull lady, ſending word before hand, that ſhe would be at <hi>Saluſs</hi> ſuch a day; whereupon the Marqueſſe ſent a troope to welcome her, and prepared the Court for her intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: the bruit of which yet had not ſo equall a paſſage, but diuers contrarious opinions thus bandied themſelues; ſome abſolutely condemned the inconſtancie of the lord, others de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored the miſfortune of the lady; ſome repined to ſée a man ſo cruell againſt ſo great worthineſſe, others exemplified her praiſes to all eternitie; ſome were tranſported with the
<pb facs="tcp:19585:15"/> gallant youth and comelineſſe of this now bewtifull Virgine, others preſumed to parallel the faire <hi>Griſel,</hi> but that ſhée had ſtepped a little before her in yeeres: ſome harped vpon her great Nobilitie and high Lineage, others compared the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wifes vertue and true wiſedome; ſome excuſed their lord, by the loue to his Country, others excuſed the lady, by the nature of the aduerſitie, vntill the approach of the faire Virgine and the young Noble man in her company, extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed all former conceits, and ſet them to a new worke, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this ſpectacle, wherein the young lady, and her braue brother had ſuch preeminence: nor knew the Earle of <hi>Paniche</hi> himſelfe or any of the company on either ſide, that they were his owne children by <hi>Griſel,</hi> but meerely ſtrangers, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for this new mariage. So the great Marqueſſe made good ſemblance, and with his accuſtomed courtlineſſe welcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them all to the Palace.</p>
               <p>The very next morning (or, if you will, the day before) he ſent a Meſſenger for <hi>Griſel</hi> to come vnto him in the very ſame manner as ſhee was, who protracted no time, but preſently attended her lord: at her approach he was ſomewhat appalled: but yet ſetting (as wee ſay) the beſt foot forward, hee thus procéeded.</p>
               <p>The lady <hi>(Griſel)</hi> with whom I muſt marrie, will bee here to morrow by this time, and the feaſt is prepared according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; now becauſe there is none ſo well acquainted with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of my Palace, and diſpoſition of my ſelfe as you, I would haue you, for all this baſe attire, addreſſe your wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the ordering of the buſineſſe, appointing ſuch officers as is befitting, and diſpoſing the roomes, according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées and eſtate of the perſons: let the lady haue the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the mariage chamber, and the young lord the pleaſure of the gallery, let the reſt be lodged in the Courts, and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort vpon the ſides of the garden: let the viands bee plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, and the ceremonies maintained; let the ſhowes bee ſumptuous, and the paſtimes as it becommeth: in a word, let nothing be wanting, which may ſet forth my honour, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light the people.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19585:16"/>
               <p>My Lord, ſaith ſhée, I euer tould you, I took pleaſure in nothing but your contentment, and whatſoeuer might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to your delight, therein conſiſted my ioy and happineſſe: therefore make no queſtion of my diligence and duty in this, or any other thing which it ſhal pleaſe you to impoſe vpon me: and ſo like a poore ſeruant ſhée preſently addreſſed herſelfe to the buſineſſe of the houſe; performing ell things with ſuch a quicknes and grace, that each one wondred at her goodneſſe and faire demeanour, and many murmured to ſée her put to ſuch a triall. But the day of entertainement is now comne: and when the faire lady approached, her very preſence had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extinguiſhed the impreſſion of <hi>Griſels</hi> worthineſſe: for ſome vnconſtant humouriſts gaue way to the alteration, not blaming the Marqueſſe for ſuch a change. But when the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers were made acquainted with the Fortune of <hi>Griſel;</hi> and ſaw her faire demeanour, they could not but eſtéeme her a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of great vertue and honour; being more amaſed at her patience, then at the mutability of mans condition; till at laſt ſhée approached the lady, and taking her by the hand, vſed this ſpéech.</p>
               <p>Lady, if it were not his pleaſure that may command to bid you welcome, yet me thinks there is a kinde of ouer-ruling grace from nature in you, that muſt exact a reſpect vnto you. And as for you, yong lord, I can ſay no more, but if I might haue my deſires ſatisfied in this world, they ſhould be imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to wiſh you well, and to endeauour all things for your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement indéed. To the reſt I afford what is befitting; deſiring them, that if any deficiency amate their expectation, they would impute it either to my ignorance, or negligence: for it is the pleaſure of him, in whoſe will is all my pleaſure, that in all ſufficiency you ſhould haue haue regard and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And ſo ſhée conducted them to their ſeuerall chambers, where they repoſed themſelues awhile, till the time of dinner inuited them to repaſt. When all things were prepared, and the ſolemnity of placing the gueſts finiſhed, the Marqueſſe ſent for <hi>Griſel;</hi> and riſing on his féet, took her by the hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them all, erecting his body, and elating his vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> in this
<pb facs="tcp:19585:16"/> manner: You ſee the lady is heere I meane to marry: and the company gloriouſly prepared to witnes the ſame: are you therefore contented that I ſhall thus diſpoſe of my ſelfe, and do quietly yéeld to the alteration?</p>
               <p>My lord, replied ſhe before them all, wherein as a woman I might be faulty, I will not now diſpute: but becauſe I am your wife, and haue deuoted my ſelfe to obedience, I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to delight in nothing but your pleaſure: ſo that if this match be deſigned for your good, and determined by your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, I am much ſatisfied, and more then much conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And for you lady, I wiſh you the delights of your marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and the honour of your husband, many yeares of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the fruits of a chaſte wedlock: only gracious lord, take héed of one thing, that you trie not this new bride as you haue done your ould wife: for ſhe is yong, and peraduenture of another ſtraine, and ſo may want of that patience and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, which I, poore I, haue endured.</p>
               <p>Till this, he held out brauely: but nature ouercomming re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and conſidering with what ſtrange variety his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe had paſſed, hee could not anſwere a word for teares, and all the company ſtood confounded at the matter, wondring what would be the end of the buſineſſe, and the ſucceſſe of the extaſie: But to draw them out of their doubts, the next Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall determine the controuerſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. The Oration of the Marqueſſe to his wife, and the diſcouery of her children, to her great ioy, and the contentment of all the company.</head>
               <p>AFter a little reducement of his paſſion, and that time, and further meditation had diſpoſed his ſenſes to their perfect eſtate, the Marqueſſe graciouſly anſwered:</p>
               <p>Thou wonder of women, and Champion of true vertue; I am aſhamed of my imperfections, and tyred with abuſing thee, I haue tryed thée beyond reaſon, and thou haſt forborne mee
<pb facs="tcp:19585:17"/> beyond modeſty: beleeue it therefore, I will haue no wife but thy ſelfe, and when God hath thought thée too good for the earth, I will (if it be not too much ſuperſtition) pray to thée in heauen. Oh, 'tis a pleaſure to be acquainted with thy worth, and to come néere thy goodnes maketh a man better then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For without controuerſie, except thou hadſt béene ſent from aboue, then couldſt neuer haue acted a goddeſſes part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe: and therefore ſéeing I haue vſed thée ſo vnkindly héer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, I proteſt neuer to diſquiet thée héereafter: and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my cruelty extended againſt thée in bereauing thée of thy children, my loue ſhall now make amends in reſtoring thy daughter. For this my new bride is ſhée; and this wanton, her brother: thank this great lady (my ſiſter) for their bringing vp, and this man (you knowe him well enough) for his ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Bée not amaſed at the matter, I haue related a truth, and will confirme it on my honour: only ſit downe till the dinner is done, and bid the company welcome in this poore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tire: for the ſun will break through ſlender clouds, and vertue ſhine in baſe array. I could much dilate the matter, but it is time to end, leſt the circumſtances will neuer end. This deuice of the Marqueſſes, of kiſſing her ſo louingly, and ſetting her downe by him ſo diſcréetly, did much good. For the company had time to diſpute of the miracle, and the yong lady reaſon to prepare her obedience; which, no ſooner was the dinner finiſhed, but ſhée as ſoone performed, nothing thought vpon but ioy at the matter, and wonder at the accident: euery one pleaſed to ſée ſuch a vnity of goodnes, and all delighted to haue a buſineſſe ſo well concluded. But ſéeing time had vnclaſped a booke of ſuch iollity, there was now no further diſputing: For the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies flocked about her to attend her into the chamber; where the yong Princeſſe her daughter was as ready as the beſt to apparell her: ſo that when ſhée came amongſt them againe, ſhe ſhined like the Sun after a tempeſt, and ſeemed more glorious, becauſe her continued modeſty kept her from all inſulting and vaine glorious brauery.</p>
               <p>Thus was the Marqueſſe inueſted as it were with a new bleſſedneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe continued in her ould con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired
<pb facs="tcp:19585:17"/> and reuerenced for her worth, as he was eſtéemed and regarded for his wiſdom: the Nobles applying themſelues to renown his eſtate, and the People proud they had ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to obey, eſpecially ſatisfied when the poore <hi>Ianicola</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uanced to his Councell, and made Gouernor of his Palace; wherein hee behaued himſelfe ſo well, that for ten yeares hee ſtill liued as he had béene bred a Courtier; and died w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> memory of a good report. <hi>Griſel</hi> laſted thirty yeare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter him: and all went to their graues in good times the Country renowned ouer the world for their admirable gouernment, and famoſed for this extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wonder.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Non nulla difficilis (vt ita dicam) neque paſſio, neque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>uius non ſufferre queat pondus hominis natura.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Euripides Oreſtei.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
